Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 41: Clinical Management of the Preeclampsia.
Syndrome Diagnosis And Evaluation.
Consideration For Delivery.
Severe Preeclampsia And Eclampsia.
Magnesium Sulfate.
Severe Hypertension Treatment.
Persistent Severe Postpartum Hypertension.
Long-Term Consequences.
References.
Preeclampsia remains one of the leading causes of death and severe maternal morbidity.
This chapter discusses many clinical aspects of the preeclampsia syndrome and its management after recognition.
Also presented are the longterm consequences that may accrue in affected women.
The pathophysiology of preeclampsia was detailed in Chapter 40.
Diagnosis And Evaluation.
# Diagnosis.
In routine prenatal care, gravidas are seen more often during the third trimester, and this aids early detection of preeclampsia.
However, it cannot always be diagnosed definitively.
Increases in systolic and diastolic blood pressure can be either normal physiological changes or signs of developing pathology.
Women without overt hypertension, but in whom the early development of preeclampsia is suspected, are seen more frequently.
Heightened surveillance permits recognition of ominous changes in blood pressure, critical laboratory findings, and clinical signs and symptoms.
Outpatient surveillance continues unless overt hypertension, proteinuria, headache, visual changes, or epigastric pain supervene.
At Parkland Hospital, women with new-onset overt hypertension—either diastolic pressures ≥90 mm Hg or systolic pressures ≥140 mm Hg—are admitted to exclude preeclampsia or to define its severity.
# Evaluation.
With hospitalization, a systematic evaluation begins: • Detailed examination, which is coupled with daily scrutiny for headache, visual changes, or epigastric pain • Daily weight measurement to identify rapid weight gain • Quantification of proteinuria or a urine protein: creatinine ratio • Blood pressure readings with an appropriate-size cuff every 4 hours, unless previously elevated, which would mandate more frequent readings • Measurements of serum creatinine and hepatic transaminase levels
and a hemogram that includes a platelet count.
The frequency of testing is determined by hypertension severity.
Although some recommend assessment of serum uric acid and lactate dehydrogenase levels and coagulation, their value has been questioned (Chescheir, 2019; CondeAgudelo, 2015) • Evaluation of fetal size and well-being and amnionic fluid volume • Reduced physical activity may have benefits, although evidence is not robust.
Still investigational as a clinical tool, measurements of placental growth factor (PlGF) and soluble fms-like tyrosine kinase 1 (sF1t-1) levels will likely be available to help predict preeclampsia (Barton, 2020; Chappell, 2013; Zeisler, 2016).
Chapter 40 (p. 694) describes their role in preeclampsia genesis.
In sum, evaluation goals are early identification of preeclampsia and then management until timely delivery.
Complete abatement of all signs and symptoms is uncommon until after delivery.
If severe preeclampsia is diagnosed using the criteria in Table 40-2 (p. 690), further management is subsequently described.
# Consideration for Delivery.
With gestational hypertension, its morbidity and management vary depending on hypertension severity, presence of preeclampsia, and gestational age of the fetus.
The basic management objectives for any pregnancy complicated by preeclampsia are: (1) termination of pregnancy with the least possible trauma to mother and fetus, (2) birth of a healthy newborn that subsequently thrives, and (3) complete restoration of health to the mother.
In many with preeclampsia, especially those at or near term, all three objectives are served equally well by induction of labor.
Termination of pregnancy is the only known cure for preeclampsia.
Headache, visual changes, or epigastric pain are indicative that convulsions may be imminent, and oliguria is another ominous sign.
Severe preeclampsia almost always demands anticonvulsant and antihypertensive therapy, followed by delivery.
Treatment
for eclampsia is identical.
Prime objectives are to forestall convulsions, control blood pressure to prevent intracranial hemorrhage and serious damage to other organs, and deliver a healthy newborn.
This is true even when the cervix is unfavorable.
Labor induction is carried out, usually with preinduction cervical ripening .
Concerns stemming from an unfavorable cervix, a perceived sense of urgency because of preeclampsia severity, and a need to coordinate neonatal intensive care have led some to advocate for cesarean delivery.
In an earlier study from Parkland Hospital, Alexander and colleagues (1999) reviewed 278 singleton liveborn neonates weighing 750 to 1500 g delivered of women with severe preeclampsia.
In half of the women, labor was induced, and induction was successful in accomplishing vaginal delivery in a third.
Similar data were reported from the Consortium on Safe Labor .
In this study, half of 914 women with severe preeclampsia underwent induction, and half of these were delivered vaginally.
Others have reported similar observations (Alanis, 2008; Roland, 2017).
For these reasons, we attempt labor induction and reserve cesarean delivery for other obstetrical indications.
With preeclampsia without severe features, optimal delivery timing has not been widely studied.
A randomized trial of 756 women with mild preeclampsia supported delivery after 37 weeks’ gestation .
This practice is also supported by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a).
At Parkland Hospital, we deliver women with preeclampsia without severe features at 38 weeks’ gestation.
With a preterm fetus, the tendency is to delay delivery to help reduce the risk of neonatal death or serious morbidity from prematurity.
Such a policy certainly is justified in milder cases.
Assessments of fetal well-being and placental function are performed, especially when the fetus is immature.
To assess these, most recommend frequent performance of nonstress testing or biophysical profiles, which are described in Chapter 20 (p. 392).
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2021a,b) recommends consideration for antenatal surveillance twice weekly for those with gestational hypertension and nonsevere features and daily testing for those with severe features.
With late-preterm fetuses, that is, those between 34 and 36 weeks’ gestation, the decision to deliver is less clear (Barton, 2011; Langenveld, 2011).
The Dutch HYPITAT-II study randomly assigned women with nonsevere hypertension between 34 and 37 weeks to immediate delivery or to expectant management .
Immediate delivery reduced the risks for adverse maternal outcomes—1.1 versus 3.1 percent.
However, it increased the risk for neonatal respiratory distress syndrome— 5.7 versus 1.7 percent.
In a more recent study, 901 women at 34 to <37 weeks’ gestation with nonsevere preeclampsia were randomly assigned to early delivery or expectant management .
A third of each group self-stratified into intervals of 34, 35, and 36 weeks’ gestation.
For women in the immediate delivery group, rates of the primary maternal outcomes, which were features of severe preeclampsia, were significantly lower than in the expectant group.
Conversely, rates of adverse perinatal outcomes, which were perinatal deaths or neonatal unit admission, were significantly greater in the immediate delivery group.
Similar findings were reported by other (Bernardes, 2019; Chatzakis, 2021).
Last, the PEACOCK study found that angiogenic biomarkers did not help determine the need for delivery in latepreterm preeclampsia .
At Parkland Hospital, we favor an active management approach given the maternal risks of expectant management.
However, if preeclampsia is nonsevere, we routinely induce after 38 completed weeks.
# Inpatient or Outpatient Care.
For women with mild to moderate stable hypertension, whether or not preeclampsia has been confirmed, monitoring is continued.
During surveillance, reduced physical activity throughout much of the day, at least intuitively, seems reasonable.
Complete bed rest
was not recommended in the prior consensus work of the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists’ Task Force on Hypertension in Pregnancy (2013).
Also, the Society for Maternal-Fetal Medicine (2020b) suggests that activity restriction not be prescribed for women with hypertensive disorders.
Complete bed rest is pragmatically unachievable because of the severe restrictions it places on otherwise well women.
It likely also predisposes to thromboembolism (Knight, 2007; McCarty-Singleton, 2014).
To reduce activity, several studies have addressed the benefits of inpatient care and outpatient management.
The concept of prolonged hospitalization for women with hypertension arose during the 1970s.
At Parkland Hospital, an inpatient antepartum unit was established in 1973 by Dr. Peggy Whalley to provide care for such women.
Initial results from this unit were reported by Hauth (1976) and Gilstrap (1978) and their coworkers.
Most hospitalized women have a beneficial response characterized by amelioration or improvement of hypertension.
These women are not “cured,” and nearly 90 percent have recurrent hypertension before or during labor.
By 2020, more than 10,000 nulliparas with mild to moderate, early-onset hypertension during pregnancy had been managed successfully in this unit.
This relatively simple unit requires modest nursing care, no drugs other than iron and folate supplements, and few essential laboratory tests.
Provider costs—not charges—for this care are minimal compared with the cost of neonatal intensive care for a preterm neonate.
Importantly, thromboembolic disease has been rare in these women.
Many clinicians believe that further hospitalization is not warranted if hypertension abates within a few days, and this has emboldened third-party payers to deny inpatient reimbursement.
Consequently, many women with mild to moderate hypertension are managed at home.
For women in vulnerable sociodemographic home situations, this strategy may not be feasible.
In other groups, outpatient management may continue as long as preeclampsia syndrome does not worsen and fetal jeopardy is not suspected.
Decreased activity is recommended, and women are encouraged to report symptoms.
Home blood pressure and urine protein monitoring or frequent evaluations by a visiting nurse may be beneficial.
To assess this approach, 1182 nulliparas with mild gestational hypertension—20 percent had proteinuria—were managed with home care .
Their mean gestational ages were 32 to 33 weeks at enrollment and 36 to 37 weeks at delivery.
Severe preeclampsia developed in approximately 20 percent, two women had eclampsia, and 3 percent developed hemolysis, elevated liver enzyme levels, and low platelet count (HELLP) syndrome.
Perinatal outcomes were generally good.
In approximately 20 percent, fetal growth was restricted, and the perinatal mortality rate was 4.2 deaths in 1000 births.
Table 41-1.
presents two studies that compare continued hospitalization and outpatient care.
In the first trial, after hospital evaluation, 218 women with mild gestational nonproteinuric hypertension were randomly assigned to continued hospitalization versus home care .
The mean hospitalization duration was 22.2 days for women with inpatient management compared with only 6.5 days in the home care group.
Severe hypertension and preterm delivery before 34 and before 37 weeks’ gestation were significantly increased twofold in the outpatient group.
Despite this, maternal and newborn outcomes were otherwise similar.
TABLE 41-1.
Randomized Clinical Trials Comparing Hospitalization Versus Routine Care for Women with Mild Gestational Hypertension or Preeclampsia 1 Another approach, popular in Europe, is day care.
In the second trial , 374 women with gestational hypertension were randomized to either day care or inpatient care .
Almost 95 percent had mild to moderate hypertension and 86 women had ≥1+ proteinuria.
There were no perinatal deaths, and none of the women developed eclampsia or HELLP syndrome.
Costs for either scheme were not significantly
different, and general satisfaction favored day care.
In sum, either inpatient or close outpatient management is appropriate for a woman with mild de novo hypertension, including those with nonsevere preeclampsia.
Keys to success are close surveillance and patients with home support and access to care.
# Antihypertensive Therapy for Mild to Moderate.
Hypertension Antihypertensive drugs have been evaluated to prolong pregnancy or modify perinatal outcomes in pregnancies complicated by various hypertensive disorders.
Treatment for women with chronic hypertension complicating pregnancy is discussed in Chapter 53 (p. 949).
Drug treatment for early mild preeclampsia has been disappointing .
Sibai and associates (1987a) reported that women given labetalol had significantly lower mean blood pressures than those given a placebo.
However, mean pregnancy prolongation, gestational age at delivery, and birthweights did not differ between groups.
The cesarean delivery rate and the number of newborns admitted to special-care nurseries also were similar.
The frequency of growth-restricted neonates was doubled in women given labetalol compared with placebo—19 versus 9 percent.
Table 41-2.
Randomized Placebo-Controlled Trials of Antihypertensive Therapy for Early Mild Gestational Hypertension The three other studies listed in Table 41-2 compare labetalol or a calcium-channel blocker drugs against placebo.
Except for fewer episodes of severe hypertension, none of these studies showed any benefits from antihypertensive treatment .
One review of 49 randomized trials of antihypertensive therapy for mild to moderate gestational hypertension compared with either no treatment or placebo reached similar conclusions .
# Expectant Management of Preterm Severe Preeclampsia.
Up through the early 1990s, women with severe preeclampsia were usually immediately delivered.
Subsequently, however, another approach for women with preterm severe preeclampsia was studied.
The aim of “expectant” management was to improve neonatal outcome without compromising maternal safety.
This approach always includes careful daily—and usually more frequent—inpatient monitoring of the mother and her fetus.
Theoretically, antihypertensive therapy has potential application when severe preeclampsia develops before intact neonatal survival is expected.
Such management has been controversial and is potentially dangerous .
In one of the first studies, Sibai and the Memphis group (1985) attempted to prolong pregnancy because of fetal immaturity in 60 women with severe preeclampsia between 18 and 27 weeks.
The results were disastrous.
The perinatal mortality rate was 87 percent.
Although no mothers died, 13 suffered placental abruption, 10 had eclampsia, three developed renal failure, two had hypertensive encephalopathy, one had an intracerebral hemorrhage, and another had a ruptured hepatic hematoma.
Because of their early study, the Memphis group redefined criteria and performed a randomized trial of aggressive versus expectant management for 95 women who had severe preeclampsia but with more advanced gestations of 28 to 32 weeks .
Women with HELLP syndrome were excluded from this trial.
Aggressive management included glucocorticoid administration for fetal lung maturation followed by delivery in 48 hours.
Expectantly managed women were observed at bed rest and given either labetalol or nifedipine orally for severe hypertension.
In this study, pregnancy was prolonged for a mean of 15.4 days in the expectant management group.
An overall improvement in neonatal outcomes also was reported.
In women expectantly managed at 23 to 34 weeks’ gestation, serious complications have included placental abruption, HELLP syndrome, pulmonary edema, renal failure, and eclampsia .
Moreover, perinatal mortality rates averaged 90 per 1000 births.
Fetal-growth restriction was common, and in studies from The Netherlands, it was an astounding 94 percent (Ganzevoort, 2005a,b).
Perinatal mortality rates were disproportionately high in these growth-restricted neonates (Haddad, 2007; Shear,
2005). Table 41-3.
Maternal and Perinatal Outcomes with Expectant Management of Severe Preeclampsia from 23 to 34 Weeks Following these experiences, expectant management became more commonly practiced, with the caveat that women with HELLP syndrome or growth-restricted fetuses were usually excluded.
More recently, a prospective comparative study reported that expectant management of women with “stable” HELLP syndrome at <34 weeks may benefit mother and fetus .
The MEXPRE Latin Study was a multicenter trial that randomly assigned 267 women with severe preeclampsia at 28 to 32 weeks’ gestation to prompt delivery or to expectant management .
The perinatal mortality rate approximated 90 per 1000 in each group, and the composite neonatal morbidity outcome was not improved with expectant management.
Conversely, fetal-growth restriction—22 versus 9 percent—and placental abruption—7.6 versus 1.5 percent—were significantly higher in the group managed expectantly.
Churchill and colleagues (2018) performed a Cochrane Database review of six randomized trials of interventionist versus expectant care for severe preeclampsia between 24 and 34 weeks.
Their review had findings similar to those in Table 41-3 and suggested that expectant management was beneficial to perinatal outcome.
However, data were insufficient to establish conclusions on maternal health.
# Expectant Management of Midtrimester Preeclampsia.
Several small studies have focused on expectant management of severe preeclampsia syndrome before 28 weeks’ gestation.
In one review of eight such studies, maternal complications were common among nearly 200 women with severe preeclampsia with an onset <26 completed weeks .
Because no neonates survived when delivered before 23 weeks, most experts recommend pregnancy termination in these cases.
For women with slightly more advanced pregnancies, however, the decision is less clear.
For example, at 23 weeks’ gestation, the perinatal survival rate was 18 percent, but long-term perinatal morbidity is yet unknown.
For women with pregnancies at 24 to 26 weeks, perinatal survival approaches 60 percent, and it averages almost 90 percent for those at 26 weeks.
As shown in Table 41-4, maternal complications—especially HELLP syndrome—were commonplace and one mother died.
Perinatal mortality exceeded 50 percent.
At this time, no comparative studies attest to perinatal benefits of such expectant treatment versus early delivery in the face of serious maternal complications, which approach rates of 50 percent.
Table 41-4.
Pregnancy Outcomes with Expectant Management of Women with Severe Midtrimester Preeclampsiaa Corticosteroids for Lung Maturation To enhance fetal lung maturation, glucocorticoids have been administered to women with severe hypertension who are remote from term.
Treatment does not seem to worsen maternal hypertension, and a lower incidence of respiratory distress and improved fetal survival rates have been cited.
That said, only one randomized trial has evaluated corticosteroids given to hypertensive women for fetal lung maturation.
This trial included 218 women who had severe preeclampsia between 26 and 34 weeks’ gestation and who were randomly assigned to betamethasone or placebo administration .
Rates of neonatal complications that included respiratory distress, intraventricular hemorrhage, and death were reduced significantly when betamethasone was given compared with placebo.
On the heavily weighted negative side, there were two maternal deaths and 18 stillbirths.
We add these findings to buttress our unenthusiastic acceptance of attempts to prolong gestation in many of these women (Alexander, 2015; Bloom, 2003).
Corticosteroids to Ameliorate HELLP Syndrome Several observational studies have indicated that corticosteroid therapy would ameliorate facets of the HELLP syndrome (Añez-Aguayo, 2018; Martin, 2016).
Subsequently, at least three randomized trials aimed to evaluate the benefits of glucocorticoids given to improve the laboratory abnormalities associated with HELLP syndrome.
Fonseca and
associates (2005) randomly assigned 132 women with HELLP syndrome to either dexamethasone or placebo administration.
Outcomes assessed included hospitalization length, recovery time of abnormal laboratory test results, resolution of clinical parameters, and complications that included acute renal failure, pulmonary edema, eclampsia, and death.
None of these was significantly different between the two groups.
In another study, 105 postpartum women with HELLP syndrome were assigned to dexamethasone or placebo treatment.
Katz and colleagues (2008) found no advantage to dexamethasone .
In the third study, preeclamptic women were given either placebo or methylprednisolone if their platelet count was between 50,000 and 150,000/μL .
Again, no benefits were gained from corticosteroid therapy.
A Bolivian study did show benefits from corticosteroid therapy, however, it was not randomized (Añez-Aguayo, 2018).
Because of these findings, the 2013 Task Force does not recommend corticosteroid treatment to improve thrombocytopenia with HELLP syndrome.
Figure 41-2.
Clinical management algorithm for severe preeclampsia at <34 weeks.
HELLP = hemolysis, elevated liver enzyme levels, low platelet count; L & D = labor and delivery; MgS04= magnesium sulfate; UOP = urine output.
# Expectant Management Recommendations.
Taken in toto, these studies do not show overwhelming benefits of expectant management of severe preeclampsia in women with gestations from 24 to 32 weeks compared with maternal risks.
Despite these caveats, the Society for Maternal-Fetal Medicine (2011) has determined that such management is a reasonable alternative in selected women with severe preeclampsia before 34 weeks .
The Task Force (2013) supports this recommendation.
As shown in Table 41-5, such management calls for inpatient maternal and fetal surveillance with delivery prompted by evidence for worsening severe preeclampsia or maternal or fetal compromise.
Although attempts are made for vaginal delivery in most cases, the likelihood of cesarean delivery rises with decreasing gestational age.
Figure 41-1.
Recovery times for platelet counts and serum aspartate transaminase (AST) levels in women with HELLP syndrome assigned to receive treatment with dexamethasone or placebo.
Table 41-5.
Indications for Delivery in Women <34 Weeks’ Gestation Managed Expectantly Our view is more conservative.
Undoubtedly, the overriding reason to terminate pregnancies with severe preeclampsia is maternal safety.
Indeed, it seems obvious that a delay to prolong gestation in women with severe preeclampsia may have serious maternal consequences.
These observations are even more pertinent when considered with the absence of convincing evidence that perinatal outcomes are markedly improved by the average prolongation of pregnancy by approximately 1 week.
If undertaken, the caveats that mandate delivery shown in Table 41-5 should be strictly heeded.
# Experimental Therapies.
In preliminary studies, therapies have been used to lower serum levels of antiangiogenic factors in hopes to mitigate their adverse actions.
Some of these include therapeutic apheresis to lower sFlt-1 levels (Thadhani, 2016; Winkler, 2018).
Another novel therapy uses RNA molecules to silence placental sFlt-1 .
The proton-pump inhibitor esomeprazole was studied in women with early-onset preeclampsia .
Sildenafil citrate, a phosphodiesterase inhibitor, has been provided to promote vasodilation (Trapani, 2016; Vigil-De Gracia, 2016).
Other studies compared recombinant antithrombin infusion with placebo .
In general, none of these therapies has shown promise.
Severe Preeclampsia And Eclampsia.
Classification of preeclampsia with severe features is summarized in Table 40-2 (p. 690).
Briefly, features include systolic blood pressure ≥160 mm Hg or diastolic pressure ≥110 mm Hg; liver derangement with transaminitis; thrombocytopenia; renal insufficiency; pulmonary edema; new-onset headache; or visual changes.
Eclampsia is defined by new-onset tonicclonic, focal, or multifocal seizures in the absence of other
causes.
# Eclampsia.
The development of eclampsia appreciably raises the risk to mother and fetus .
In an earlier report, Mattar and Sibai (2000) described outcomes in 399 consecutive women with eclampsia from 1977 through 1998.
Major maternal complications included placental abruption— 10 percent, neurological deficits—7 percent, aspiration pneumonia—7 percent, pulmonary edema—5 percent, cardiopulmonary arrest—4 percent, and acute kidney injury (AKI)—4 percent.
Moreover, 1 percent of these women died.
Several subsequent reports similarly described excessive maternal morbidity and mortality rates with eclampsia that also included HELLP syndrome, pulmonary embolism, and stroke (Andersgaard, 2006; Knight, 2007).
Almost without exception—but at times unnoticed— preeclampsia precedes convulsions.
Eclampsia is most common in the last trimester and becomes increasingly frequent as term approaches.
Postpartum, the incidence of eclampsia has declined during the past decade.
Improved access to prenatal care, earlier detection of antepartum preeclampsia, and prophylactic use of magnesium sulfate are explanations .
Other diagnoses should be considered in women with convulsions more than 48 hours postpartum or in women with focal neurological deficits, prolonged coma, or atypical eclampsia.
# Clinical Findings with Eclampsia.
Eclamptic seizures may be violent, and the woman must be protected, especially her airway.
So forceful are the muscular movements that the woman may throw herself out of her bed, and if not protected, her tongue is bitten by the violent action of the jaws .
This phase, in which the muscles alternately contract and relax, may last approximately a minute.
Figure 41-3.
Hematoma of tongue from laceration during an eclamptic convulsion.
Thrombocytopenia may have contributed to the bleeding.
Gradually, the muscular movements become smaller and less frequent, and finally the woman lies motionless.
After a seizure, the woman is postictal, but in some, a coma of variable duration ensues.
When the convulsions are infrequent, the woman usually recovers some degree of consciousness after each attack.
As the woman arouses, a semiconscious combative state may ensue.
In severe cases, coma persists from one convulsion to another, and death may result.
Rarely, a single convulsion may be followed by coma from which the woman may never emerge.
As a rule, however, death does not occur until after frequent convulsions.
Last, and also rarely, convulsions continue unabated—status epilepticus—and require deep sedation and even general anesthesia to obviate anoxic encephalopathy.
The respiratory rate after an eclamptic convulsion usually rises and may reach 50 or more per minute in response to hypercarbia, lactic acidemia, and transient hypoxia.
Cyanosis may be observed in severe cases.
High fever is a grave sign as it likely emanates from cerebrovascular hemorrhage.
Proteinuria is usually present, and a fourth of women with severe preeclampsia have some degree of AKI .
Urine output may be diminished appreciably, and occasionally anuria develops.
Hemoglobinuria may be seen, but hemoglobinemia is rare.
Edema may be pronounced .
Figure 41-4.
Severe edema in a young nullipara with antepartum preeclampsia.
Fingerprint indentations from clinical assessment can be seen on both shins.
Rings at the ankles formed from elastic sock bands.
Reproduced with permission from Dr. Nidhi Shah.
With severe preeclampsia, urinary output rises after delivery and is usually an early sign of improvement.
With renal dysfunction, serum creatinine levels are serially monitored.
Proteinuria and edema ordinarily disappear within a week postpartum.
In most cases, blood pressure returns to normal within a few days to 2 weeks after delivery .
As subsequently discussed, persisting and severe hypertension likely predicts underlying chronic vascular disease.
In antepartum eclampsia, labor may begin spontaneously shortly after convulsions ensue and may progress rapidly.
If the seizures develop during labor, contractions may increase in frequency
and intensity, and the duration of labor may be shortened.
Because of maternal hypoxemia and lactic acidemia caused by convulsions, fetal bradycardia often follows a seizure .
In our experiences, the fetal heart rate usually recovers within 2 to 10 minutes.
If it persists more than 10 minutes, another cause of bradycardia, such as placental abruption, should be considered.
Figure 41-5.
Fetal heart rate tracing shows fetal bradycardia following an intrapartum eclamptic convulsion.
Bradycardia resolved and beat—to—beat variability returned approximately 5 minutes following the seizure.
Pulmonary edema may follow shortly after eclamptic convulsions or several hours later.
This complication is further explored on page 724.
Occasionally, sudden death occurs synchronously with an eclamptic seizure, or it follows shortly thereafter.
Most often in these cases, a massive cerebral hemorrhage is the cause (Fig. 40-11, p. 700).
Hemiplegia may result from sublethal hemorrhage.
Cerebral hemorrhages are more likely in older women with underlying chronic hypertension.
For women with a neurological deficit after an eclamptic seizure, consideration is given for emergent cranial computed tomography (CT) scanning.
Up to 5 percent of women with eclampsia have altered consciousness, including persistent coma, following a seizure.
This may be due to extensive cerebral edema, and associated transtentorial herniation may cause death .
In approximately 10 percent of eclamptic women, some degree of blindness follows a seizure.
The causes of impaired vision which usually improves postpartum, are discussed in Chapter 40 (p. 701).
Rarely, eclampsia is followed by psychosis, and the woman becomes violent.
This may last for several days to 2 weeks.
The prognosis for return to normal function is good, provided mental illness was not preexisting.
It is presumed to be similar to postpartum psychosis discussed in Chapter 64 (p. 1148).
Antipsychotic medications have been effective in the few cases of posteclampsia psychosis treated at Parkland Hospital.
Generally, eclampsia is more likely to be diagnosed too frequently rather than overlooked.
Epilepsy, encephalitis, meningitis, brain tumor, neurocysticercosis, amnionic fluid embolism, postdural puncture cephalalgia, and ruptured cerebral aneurysm during late pregnancy or in the puerperium may simulate eclampsia.
Until other such causes are excluded, however, all pregnant women with convulsions should be considered to have eclampsia.
As a pragmatic rule, loading with magnesium sulfate should be considered while alternate diagnoses are explored.
Management Of Severe Preeclampsiaeclampsia.
Most eclampsia regimens in the United States adhere to a similar philosophy: • Control or prevent convulsions using an intravenous loading dose of magnesium sulfate.
This is followed by maintenance dosing, usually given intravenously • Provide intermittent antihypertensive medication to lower dangerously high blood pressure • Avoid diuretics unless pulmonary edema is obvious; limit intravenous fluid administration unless fluid loss is excessive; and avoid hyperosmotic agents • Deliver the fetus to resolve preeclampsia.
# Magnesium Sulfate.
This parenterally administered agent is an effective anticonvulsant and avoids producing central nervous system depression.
It may be given intravenously by continuous infusion or intramuscularly by intermittent injection .
A third option is intermittent, intravenous, 2-g injections .
Dosages for severe preeclampsia mirror those for eclampsia.
Because labor and delivery is a more likely time for seizures to develop, women with severe preeclampsia or eclampsia usually are given magnesium sulfate during labor and for 24 hours postpartum.
In the United States, magnesium sulfate is almost universally administered intravenously.
Of concern, magnesium sulfate solutions, although inexpensive to prepare, are not readily available in all parts of the developing world.
Even if solutions are available, the technology to infuse them may not be.
Thus, the drug can be administered
intramuscularly, and this is as effective as intravenous infusion (Pritchard, 1955, 1975, 1984; Salinger, 2013).
Table 41-6.
Magnesium Sulfate Dosage Schedule for Severe Preeclampsia and Eclampsia Magnesium sulfate is not given to treat hypertension.
Magnesium ion most likely exerts a specific anticonvulsant action on the cerebral cortex.
Typically, the mother stops convulsing after the initial 4-g loading dose.
By an hour or two, she regains consciousness sufficiently to be oriented to place and time.
The magnesium sulfate dosage regimens presented in Table 41-6 usually result in increased plasma magnesium levels.
Data from Brookfield and associates (2016) are illustrated in Figure 41-6.
When magnesium sulfate is given to arrest an eclamptic seizure, up to 15 percent of women will have a subsequent convulsion.
If so, an additional 2-g dose of magnesium sulfate in a 20-percent solution is slowly administered intravenously.
In a small woman, this additional 2-g dose may be used once, but it can be given twice if needed in a larger woman.
In only 5 of 245 women with eclampsia at Parkland Hospital was it necessary to use alternative supplementary anticonvulsant medication to control seizures .
For these, a small dose of a short-acting benzodiazepine such as midazolam or lorazepam is given intravenously.
Their prolonged use is avoided because of an associated higher mortality rate from aspiration pneumonia .
Figure 41-6.
Serum magnesium concentration in normotensive and preeclamptic women following a 4-g loading dose of magnesium sulfate and 2 g/h infusion.
Maintenance magnesium sulfate therapy has traditionally been continued for 24 hours after delivery.
For eclampsia that develops postpartum, magnesium sulfate is administered for 24 hours after the onset of convulsions.
A few investigators have truncated this therapy duration to 12 hours and reported no seizures (Anjum, 2016; Ehrenberg, 2006; Kashanian, 2016).
Outcomes have also been reported when magnesium sulfate therapy was stopped after delivery (Ludmir, 2017; Vigil-De Gracia, 2018).
These studies are relatively small, and the abbreviated magnesium sulfate regimens need further study before being routinely implemented.
Pharmacology and Toxicology Parenterally administered magnesium is cleared almost totally by renal excretion, and magnesium clearance rate is approximately a third of glomerular filtration rate (GFR) determined by creatinine clearance.
Magnesium intoxication is unusual when the GFR is normal or only slightly reduced.
Adequate urine output usually correlates with preserved GFR.
That said, magnesium excretion is not urine flow dependent, and urinary volume per unit time does not, per se, predict renal function.
Thus, serum creatinine levels must be measured to confirm a decreased GFR.
Eclamptic convulsions are almost always prevented or arrested by plasma magnesium levels maintained at 4 to 7 mEq/L, 4.8 to 8.4 mg/dL, or 2.0 to 3.5 mmol/L.
However, one review of magnesium pharmacokinetics showed that most regimens result in much lower serum magnesium levels .
This was especially true if only 1 g/hr was infused .
Importantly, the obesity epidemic has affected these observations .
Tudela and colleagues (2013) described our results from Parkland Hospital with magnesium administration to obese women.
More than 60 percent of women who had a body mass index (BMI) >30 kg/m2 and who were receiving a 2-g/hr dose had subtherapeutic levels at 4 hours.
Thus, most obese women would require 3 g/hr to maintain effective plasma levels.
That said, most currently do not recommend routine magnesium level measurements (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2020a; Royal College of Obstetricians and Gynaecologists, 2006).
Patellar reflexes disappear when the plasma magnesium level reaches 10 mEq/L—approximately 12 mg/dL—presumably because of a curariform action.
This sign serves to warn of impending magnesium toxicity.
When plasma levels rise above 10 mEq/L, breathing weakens.
At 12 mEq/L or higher levels, respiratory paralysis and respiratory arrest
follow .
Treating with calcium gluconate or calcium chloride, 1 g intravenously, coupled with magnesium sulfate discontinuation, usually reverses mild to moderate respiratory depression.
One of these agents should be readily available whenever magnesium is being infused.
Unfortunately, the effects of intravenously administered calcium may be short-lived if a steady-state toxic magnesium level has been reached.
For severe respiratory depression and arrest, prompt tracheal intubation and mechanical ventilation are lifesaving.
Direct toxic effects on the myocardium from high levels of magnesium sulfate are uncommon .
Because magnesium is cleared almost exclusively by renal excretion, our described dosages of magnesium sulfate will become excessive if the GFR is substantially decreased.
The initial 4- or 6-g loading dose of magnesium sulfate can be safely administered regardless of renal function.
It is important to administer the standard loading dose and not to reduce it.
A loading dose achieves the desired therapeutic level, and the infusion maintains the steady-state level.
Thus, only the maintenance infusion rate should be altered for those with a diminished GFR.
Renal function is estimated by measuring plasma creatinine.
Whenever plasma creatinine levels are >1.0 mg/mL, serial serum magnesium levels are determined to guide the infusion rate .
After a 4-g intravenous dose is administered during 15 minutes, mean arterial pressure falls slightly and is accompanied by a 13-percent rise in cardiac index .
Thus, magnesium lowers systemic vascular resistance and mean arterial pressure.
At the same time, cardiac output is increased.
These findings are coincidental with transient nausea and flushing, and the cardiovascular effects persist for only 15 minutes despite continued magnesium infusion.
Magnesium-induced vasodilation is weaker in placental vessels because of diminished calcium-channel activity .
Thurnau and coworkers (1987) showed that magnesium therapy led to a small but significant rise in the cerebrospinal fluid’s total magnesium concentration.
The magnitude was directly proportional to the corresponding serum concentration.
Other Effects Magnesium has anticonvulsant and neuroprotective effects in animal models.
Some proposed mechanisms of action include: (1) reduced presynaptic release of the neurotransmitter glutamate, (2) blockade of glutamatergic Nmethyl-D-aspartate (NMDA) receptors, (3) potentiation of adenosine action, (4) improved calcium buffering by mitochondria, and (5) blockage of calcium entry via voltage-gated channels (Arango, 2008; Wang, 2012).
In the uterus, relatively high serum magnesium concentrations depress myometrial contractility.
Inhibition of uterine contractility is magnesium dose dependent, and serum levels of at least 8 to 10 mEq/L are needed to inhibit uterine contractions .
With the suggested magnesium sulfate regimens for seizure prevention, prolonged myometrial depression has not been observed.
A transient decline in activity during and immediately after the initial intravenous loading dose can be seen (Leveno, 1998; Witlin, 1997).
Blood loss at delivery is not increased by standard magnesium sulfate treatment .
# Neuroprophylaxis—Prevention of Seizures.
Several randomized trials have tested the efficacy of seizure prophylaxis for women with gestational hypertension, with or without proteinuria.
In all, magnesium sulfate was superior to the comparator agent to prevent eclampsia.
Four of the larger studies are summarized in Table 41-7.
In the study from Parkland Hospital, magnesium sulfate therapy was superior to phenytoin to prevent seizures in women with gestational hypertension or preeclampsia .
In another study, magnesium sulfate and nimodipine, which is a calcium-channel blocking drug with specific cerebral vasodilator activity, were compared in 1650 women with severe preeclampsia .
The rate of eclampsia was more than threefold higher for women allocated to the nimodipine group—2.6 versus 0.8 percent.
Table 41-7.
Randomized Comparative Trials of Prophylaxis with
Magnesium Sulfate and Placebo or Another Anticonvulsant in Women with Gestational Hypertension The largest comparative study was Magnesium Sulfate for Prevention of Eclampsia reported by the Magpie Trial Collaboration Group (2002).
More than 10,000 women with severe preeclampsia from 33 countries were randomly allocated to treatment with magnesium sulfate or placebo.
Women given magnesium had a 58-percent significantly lower risk of eclampsia than those given placebo.
Maternal mortality and placental abruption rates also were decreased.
Child behavior at 18 months did not differ between groups .
Who Should Be Given Magnesium Sulfate?
Magnesium will prevent proportionately more seizures in women with correspondingly worse disease.
However, severity is difficult to quantify, and thus deciding which woman might benefit most from neuroprophylaxis is sometimes difficult.
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a) recommends that women with either eclampsia or severe preeclampsia should be given magnesium sulfate prophylaxis.
Again, criteria that establish “severity” are not universal.
Thus, the conundrum is whether women with “nonsevere” gestational hypertension or preeclampsia should receive magnesium neuroprophylaxis.
We found that approximately 1 woman in 100 who has nonsevere preeclampsia but who is not given magnesium sulfate prophylaxis can be expected to have a seizure.
A fourth of these women likely will require emergent cesarean delivery and be exposed to the attendant maternal and perinatal morbidity from general anesthesia.
From this, the major question regarding management of nonsevere gestational hypertension remains whether it is acceptable to avoid unnecessary treatment of 99 women to risk eclampsia in one.
The answer appears to be yes, as suggested by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a).
At Parkland Hospital, our policy is to give magnesium neuroprophylaxis to women with preeclampsia with severe features, and conservatively to those with proteinuria hypertension (Table 40-1, p. 689).
Fetal and Neonatal Effects Magnesium administered parenterally promptly crosses the placenta to achieve equilibrium in fetal serum and less so in amnionic fluid (GortzakUzan, 2005; Narasimhulu, 2017).
Magnesium sulfate has small but significant effects on the fetal heart rate pattern and specifically on beat-to-beat variability .
One study showed a lower baseline heart rate that was within the normal range; decreased variability; and fewer prolonged decelerations .
Overall, maternal magnesium therapy appears safe for perinates .
One study of more than 1500 exposed preterm neonates found no association between the need for neonatal resuscitation and cord blood magnesium levels .
Still, a few neonatal adverse events are associated with its use.
In a Parkland Hospital study of 6654 mostly term, exposed newborns, 6 percent had hypotonia .
In addition, exposed neonates had lower 1- and 5-minute Apgar scores, a higher intubation rate, and more admissions to the special care nursery.
Neonatal depression occurs only if hypermagnesemia at delivery is severe.
Observational studies suggest a protective effect of magnesium against the development of cerebral palsy in very-low- birthweight newborns .
These beneficial effects may extend to growth-restricted fetuses.
Randomized trials have also assessed neuroprotective effects for preterm neonates, and findings are discussed in Chapter 45 (p. 803).
One review expanded this possibility to include term newborns, but data were insufficient to draw conclusions .
Maternal Safety and Efficacy The multinational Eclampsia Trial Collaborative Group study (1995) involved 1687 women with eclampsia randomly allocated to one of three different anticonvulsant regimens: magnesium sulfate, diazepam, or phenytoin .
In aggregate, magnesium sulfate therapy was associated with a significantly lower incidence of recurrent seizures (9.7 percent) compared with women given phenytoin (28 percent) or diazepam (17 percent).
Moreover, the aggregate maternal death
rate of 3.2 percent with magnesium sulfate was significantly lower than that of 5.2 percent for the other two regimens.
Table 41-8.
Randomized Comparative Trials of Magnesium Sulfate versus Phenytoin and Diazepam to Prevent Recurrent Eclamptic Convulsions # Severe Hypertension Treatment.
Dangerous hypertension can cause cerebrovascular hemorrhage and hypertensive encephalopathy, and it can trigger eclamptic convulsions.
Other complications are placental abruption and congestive heart failure induced by elevated hypertensive afterload.
Studies highlight the importance of treating systolic hypertension when blood pressures are >160 mm Hg (Judy, 2019; Martin, 2005, 2016).
Because of these serious sequelae, the Working Group for the National High Blood Pressure Education Program (2000) and the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a) recommend treatment to lower systolic pressures to a level ≤160 mm Hg and diastolic pressures to ≤110 mm Hg.
Lower diastolic pressures can compromise placental perfusion.
From other observations, it seems likely that at least half of serious hemorrhagic strokes associated with preeclampsia are in women with chronic hypertension (Cunningham, 2005; Zofkie, 2018).
Long-standing hypertension results in development of Charcot–Bouchard aneurysms in the deep penetrating arteries of the lenticulostriate branch of the middle cerebral arteries.
These vessels supply the basal ganglia, putamen, thalamus, adjacent deep white matter, pons, and deep cerebellum.
These unique aneurysmal weakenings predispose these small arteries to rupture during sudden hypertensive episodes.
Several drugs are available to rapidly lower dangerously elevated blood pressure in women with pregnancy-associated hypertension.
Hydralazine, labetalol, and nifedipine are recommended as first-line agents by the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a).
Evidence supports their value to decrease stroke risk .
All three agents have equivalent efficacy.
Comparative studies of hydralazine and labetalol show similar results (Mable, 1987; Umans, 2015).
Hydralazine causes significantly more maternal tachycardia and palpitations, whereas labetalol more frequently leads to maternal hypotension and bradycardia.
Randomized trials that compared nifedipine with labetalol found neither drug definitively superior, but nifedipine lowered blood pressure more quickly (Gainder, 2019; Zulfeen, 2019).
Both drugs are associated with a reduced frequency of fetal heart rate accelerations .
Last, a study comparing nifedipine and hydralazine showed similar efficacy .
A few other generally available antihypertensive agents have been tested in clinical trials but are not widely used .
These include verapamil, nitroglycerin, nitroprusside, ketanserin, nicardipine, and nimodipine (Belfort, 2003; Cornette, 2016).
Experimental antihypertensive drugs may eventually be useful for preeclampsia treatment .
Hydralazine This antihypertensive agent is administered intravenously or intramuscularly.
An initial 5- to 10-mg dose can act as rapidly as 10 minutes.
If needed, this is followed by 10-mg doses at 15- to 20-minute intervals until a satisfactory response is achieved .
Although we will administer a third dose, the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a) recommends labetalol therapy if severe hypertension persists after the second dose.
Another regimen continuously infuses hydralazine at a rate of 0.5 to 10 mg/hr. Table 41-9.
Antihypertensive Agents for Urgent Control of Severe Hypertension For higher blood pressures, the tendency to give a larger initial dose of hydralazine should be avoided.
The response to 5- to 10-mg doses cannot be predicted by hypertension severity.
Thus, our protocol is to always administer 5 mg as the initial dose.
An adverse response to exceeding this initial dose is shown in Figure 41-7.
This woman had chronic hypertension complicated by severe superimposed preeclampsia, and hydralazine was injected more frequently than recommended.
Her blood pressure in less than 1 hour dropped
from 270/150 mm Hg to 110/80 mm Hg. Fetal heart rate decelerations characteristic of uteroplacental insufficiency became evident.
Decelerations persisted until her blood pressure was raised with rapid crystalloid infusion.
In some cases, this fetal response to diminished uterine perfusion may be confused with placental abruption and may result in unnecessary and potentially dangerous emergency cesarean delivery.
Figure 41-7.
Hydralazine was given at 5-minute intervals instead of 15-minute intervals.
The mean arterial pressure dropped from 180 to 90 mm Hg within 1 hour and was associated with fetal bradycardia.
Rapid crystalloid infusion raised the mean pressure to 115 mm Hg, and the fetus recovered.
Labetalol This effective intravenous antihypertensive agent is an α- and nonselective βblocker.
Some prefer its use to hydralazine because of fewer side effects.
Importantly, labetalol is usually not given to asthmatic women.
At Parkland Hospital, we give 10 mg intravenously initially.
If blood pressure has not declined to suitable levels in 10 minutes, 20 mg is given.
The next 10-minute incremental dose is 40 mg and is followed by another 40 mg if needed.
If a salutary response is not achieved, an 80-mg dose is provided .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2020a) recommends starting with a 10- to 20-mg intravenous bolus.
If not effective, this is followed by 20 to 80 mg every 10 to 30 minutes.
If hypertension persists, hydralazine is then given.
Nifedipine This calcium-channel blocking agent is given initially as a 10- to 20-mg oral dose of immediate release medication.
If necessary after 20 minutes, a 10- to 20-mg oral dose is repeated.
With an unsatisfactory response, labetalol is provided.
Nifedipine given sublingually is no longer recommended.
This route is associated with dangerously rapid and extensive effects.
Diuretics Potent loop diuretics can further compromise placental perfusion.
Immediate effects include redistribution of intravascular volume, which most often is already reduced in severe preeclampsia (p. 724).
Thus, before delivery, diuretics are not used to lower blood pressure (Zeeman, 2009; Zondervan, 1988).
Furosemide or similar drugs are used before delivery solely to treat pulmonary edema.
Discussed on page 725, they may have a role in treatment of postpartum hypertension.
# Fluid Therapy.
Crystalloid solution is administered routinely at a rate between 60 and 125 mL per hour, unless fluid loss is unusual from vomiting, diarrhea, diaphoresis, or excessive blood loss.
Oliguria is common with severe preeclampsia.
Coupled with the knowledge that maternal blood volume is likely constricted compared with that of normal pregnancy, it is tempting to administer intravenous fluids more vigorously.
However, controlled, conservative fluid administration is preferred for the typical woman with severe preeclampsia.
These gravidas already have excessive extracellular fluid that has inappropriately extravasated from the intravascular compartment.
Infusion of large fluid volumes enhances the maldistribution and thereby elevates the risk of pulmonary and cerebral edema (Sciscioner, 2003; Zinaman, 1985).
Thus, for preeclamptic women with anuria, small incremental boluses can be given to maintain urine output above 30 mL/hr.
Diminished intravascular volume from hemorrhage or fluid loss from vomiting or fever can similarly be replaced by gradual incremental boluses of crystalloid.
For labor analgesia with neuraxial analgesia, crystalloid solutions are infused slowly in graded amounts .
Pulmonary Edema Women with severe preeclampsia who develop pulmonary edema most often do so postpartum (Cunningham, 1986, 2012).
With pulmonary edema in the eclamptic woman, aspiration of gastric contents, which may be the result of convulsions, anesthesia, or oversedation, should be excluded.
Otherwise, in women with severe preeclampsia, three common causes of pulmonary edema are pulmonary capillary permeability edema, cardiogenic edema, or their combination.
First, in women with preeclampsia, both increased
capillary permeability and greater extravascular fluid oncotic pressure are found (Brown, 1989; Øian, 1986).
If intravenous fluid replacement is vigorous, pulmonary congestion can follow.
Second, in some women, pulmonary edema may be caused by ventricular failure from increased afterload that results from severe hypertension.
Such pulmonary edema from ventricular failure is more common in morbidly obese women and in those with chronic hypertension.
Invasive Hemodynamic Monitoring Knowledge concerning cardiovascular and hemodynamic pathophysiological alterations associated with severe preeclampsia–eclampsia has accrued from studies done using invasive monitoring and a pulmonary artery catheter (Fig. 40-5, p. 694).
Two conditions frequently cited as indications are preeclampsia associated with oliguria or with pulmonary edema .
Somewhat ironically, it is usually vigorous treatment of the former that results in most cases of the latter.
The Task Force (2013) recommends against routine invasive monitoring.
This is best reserved for women with severe preeclampsia and with accompanying cardiac disease, renal disease, or both or with refractory hypertension, oliguria, and pulmonary edema.
Preliminary data from studies using a noninvasive cardiac monitoring system need to be verified before widespread clinical application .
# Plasma Volume Expansion.
Because the preeclampsia syndrome is associated with hemoconcentration, some have infused various fluids, starch polymers, albumin concentrates, or combinations to expand blood volume.
Older studies describe serious complications—especially pulmonary edema—with volume expansion (Benedetti, 1985; Sibai, 1987b).
The Amsterdam randomized study reported by Ganzevoort and coworkers (2005a,b) was a well-designed investigation done to evaluate volume expansion.
A total of 216 women with severe preeclampsia were enrolled between 24 and 34 weeks’ gestation.
The study included women whose preeclampsia was complicated by HELLP syndrome, eclampsia, pulmonary edema, or fetal-growth restriction.
In the group randomly assigned to volume expansion, each woman was given 250 mL of 6-percent hydroxyethyl starch infused over 4 hours twice daily.
Pregnancy outcomes were compared with a control group, and none of these were significantly different.
Importantly, serious maternal morbidity and a substantive perinatal mortality rate accompanied their expectant management.
# Analgesia and Anesthesia.
During the past 25 years, the use of neuraxial analgesia for women with preeclampsia syndrome has proved ideal.
Randomized studies attest to its safety, and these trials are fully described in Chapter 25 (p. 478).
Initial problems with neuraxial analgesia included hypotension and diminished uterine perfusion caused by sympathetic blockade in preeclamptic women, who already have attenuated hypervolemia.
However, slow induction of epidural analgesia with dilute solutions of anesthetic agents counter the need for rapid infusion of large volumes of crystalloid or colloid to prevent maternal hypotension (Hogg, 1999; Wallace, 1995).
Importantly, epidural blockade avoids general anesthesia, in which the stimulation of tracheal intubation may cause sudden severe hypertension.
Such blood pressure spikes can cause pulmonary edema, cerebral edema, or intracranial hemorrhage.
Last, tracheal intubation may be particularly difficult and thus hazardous in women with airway edema due to preeclampsia .
Judicious fluid administration is essential in women with severe preeclampsia who receive regional analgesia.
Vigorous crystalloid infusion with epidural blockade in women with severe preeclampsia elevates pulmonary capillary wedge pressures .
Aggressive volume replacement in preeclamptic women raises their risk for pulmonary edema, especially in the first 72 hours postpartum (Clark, 1985; Cotton, 1986a).
Last, most cases of pharyngolaryngeal edema are related to aggressive volume therapy .
In sum, general anesthesia, epidural analgesia, or combined spinal-epidural analgesia are acceptable for women severe preeclampsia
if steps are taken to ensure a careful approach to the selected method.
At Parkland Hospital, a gentle bolus is given accompanying epidural placement .
# Blood Loss at Delivery.
Hemoconcentration or lack of normal pregnancy-induced hypervolemia is an almost predictable feature of severe preeclampsia–eclampsia (Fig. 40-7, p. 696) .
These women, who consequently lack normal pregnancy hypervolemia, may poorly tolerate even normal blood loss.
Thus, an appreciable fall in blood pressure soon after delivery most often means excessive blood loss and not sudden resolution of vasospasm and endothelial damage.
When oliguria follows delivery, the hematocrit should be evaluated frequently to help detect excessive blood loss.
If identified, hemorrhage should be treated appropriately by crystalloid and blood transfusion.
# Persistent Severe Postpartum Hypertension.
Postpartum, 8 percent of women develop de novo hypertension .
At times, controlling severe hypertension may be difficult or intravenous hydralazine or labetalol or oral immediate-release nifedipine are being used repeatedly.
In these cases, oral maintenance regimens can be given.
Examples include labetalol or another β-blocking agent; nifedipine extended release; amlodipine; or another calcium-channel blocking agent .
Women so treated are less likely to require readmission (Stamilio, 2021; Wen, 2019).
The Society for Maternal-Fetal Medicine (2020a) has developed a check list for postpartum care of women with hypertensive disorders.
Persistent hypertension is likely aggravated by pathological interstitial fluid that is now returning to the intravascular compartment, by underlying chronic hypertension, or by both (Sibai, 2012; Tan, 2002).
Nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs do not aggravate postpartum hypertension (Anastasio, 2018; Penfield, 2019).
In some women with chronic hypertension and leftventricular hypertrophy, severe postpartum hypertension can cause pulmonary edema from cardiac failure (Cunningham, 1986, 2019; Sibai, 1987a).
Furosemide Severe hypertension persists depending on the onset and length of extracellular fluid mobilization and diuresis.
Thus, it seems logical that furosemide-augmented diuresis might serve to hasten blood pressure control .
In one randomized trial of 384 women with hypertensive disorders of pregnancy, a cohort that received furosemide postpartum had significantly lower blood pressures at 7 days—6 versus 14 percent— compared with women who received placebo .
The need for antihypertensive treatment to be given at discharge in the furosemide group also was significantly reduced.
In another randomized study, women with severe postpartum preeclampsia received nifedipine plus furosemide or nifedipine alone.
The furosemide regimen significantly lowered the need for additional antihypertensive agents—8 versus 26 percent, respectively .
Conversely, in one study, torsemide had no significant benefits .
We use a simple method to estimate excessive extracellular fluid.
The postpartum weight is compared with the most recent prenatal weight, either from the last clinic visit or from admission for delivery.
Typically, soon after delivery, maternal weight should be reduced by at least 10 to 15 pounds depending on newborn and placental weight, amnionic fluid volume, and blood loss.
Because of various interventions, especially intravenous crystalloid infusions given with labor epidural analgesia or during operative vaginal or cesarean delivery, women with severe preeclampsia often have an immediate postpartum weight in excess of their last prenatal weight.
If this weight increase is associated with severe persistent postpartum hypertension, diuresis with intravenous furosemide can be helpful in controlling blood pressure.
Thrombotic Microangiopathy Occasionally, women have an atypical syndrome in which severe preeclampsia–eclampsia persists despite delivery.
Martin and associates (1995) described 18 such women whom they encountered during a 10-year period.
They advocate single or multiple plasma exchange for these women.
In some cases, 3 L of
plasma was exchanged three times before a response was forthcoming.
This is a 36- to 45-donor-unit exposure for each patient.
Others have described plasma exchange performed in postpartum women with HELLP syndrome (Förster, 2002; Obeidat, 2002).
In all of these cases, however, the distinction between HELLP syndrome and thrombotic thrombocytopenic purpura or hemolytic uremic syndrome was not clear .
In our experiences with more than 55,000 women with gestational hypertension among nearly 500,000 pregnancies cared for at Parkland Hospital through 2021, we have encountered very few women with persistent postpartum hypertension, thrombocytopenia, and renal dysfunction who were diagnosed as having a thrombotic microangiopathy .
Reversible Cerebral Vasoconstriction Syndrome This is another cause of persistent hypertension, “thunderclap” headaches, seizures, and central nervous system findings.
Reversible cerebral vasoconstriction syndrome is characterized by diffuse segmental constriction of cerebral arteries and may be associated with ischemic and hemorrhagic strokes.
This syndrome has several inciting causes that include pregnancy and particularly preeclampsia .
It is more frequent in women, and long-term sequelae are uncommon.
However, in some cases, vasoconstriction may be so severe as to cause cerebral ischemia and infarction .
We have encountered only a few women with a stroke cause by this arteriopathy .
The most appropriate management is unclear .
Long-Term Consequences.
# Future Pregnancies.
Women with preeclampsia during an index pregnancy are at risk for hypertensive and other disorders in subsequent pregnancies and later in life .
In some, but not all women, the risk for hypertension is higher in the first 6 months postpartum (Giorgione, 2021; Mulder, 2021).
Even in subsequent nonhypertensive pregnancies, women who had preterm preeclampsia have a higher risk for preterm birth and growth-restricted neonates (Connealy, 2014; Palatnik, 2016).
Generally, the earlier preeclampsia is diagnosed during the index pregnancy, the greater the likelihood of recurrence.
Women with preeclampsia near term had a recurrence risk of 23 percent, but nulliparas diagnosed with preeclampsia before 30 weeks had a recurrence risk as high as 40 percent (Bramham, 2011; Sibai 1986, 1991).
As perhaps expected, women with HELLP syndrome have a substantive risk for recurrence in subsequent pregnancies.
Even if HELLP syndrome does not recur with subsequent pregnancies, again incidences of preterm delivery, fetal-growth restriction, placental abruption, and cesarean delivery are increased (Habli, 2009; Malmström, 2020).
# Cardiovascular Morbidity.
The preeclampsia syndrome is also a marker for subsequent long-term cardiovascular morbidity (Hammad, 2020; Stuart, 2018; Wang, 2021).
Thus, women with hypertension identified during pregnancy should be evaluated during the first several months postpartum.
Table 41-10.
Some Long-Term Consequences in Women with Preeclampsia Syndrome The Working Group of the NHBPEP (2000) concluded that hypertension attributable to pregnancy should resolve within 12 weeks of delivery, and hypertension persisting beyond this time is considered chronic .
The Magpie Trial Follow-Up Collaborative Group (2007) reported that 20 percent of 3375 preeclamptic women seen at a median of 26 months postpartum had hypertension.
From one metanaalysis, a 28-percent incidence of hypertension was found within 2 years of deliveries complicated by preeclampsia .
From a Danish registry and after a mean of almost 15 years, the incidence of chronic hypertension was fivefold higher in those who had gestational hypertension, fourfold greater after mild preeclampsia, and sixfold higher after severe preeclampsia compared with women without hypertension in pregnancy .
Any hypertension during pregnancy is a risk marker for cardiovascular morbidity in later life .
As shown in data from Brouwers and coworkers (2018), the risk is greater in women with recurrent preeclampsia .
In a study from Iceland, the prevalence of ischemic heart disease—24
versus 15 percent, and of stroke—9.5 versus 6.5 percent, were increased in women who had gestational hypertension compared with normotensive controls .
In a Swedish population study of more than 400,000 women, those with recurrent preeclampsia had systolic dysfunction and a greater incidence of ischemic heart disease .
Diastolic dysfunction also is more common .
Preeclampsia is also a risk for coronary artery calcification and idiopathic cardiomyopathy (Gammill, 2018; White, 2016).
Table 41-11.
Long-Term Cardiovascular Morbidities After Recurrent Preeclampsia Compared with a Single Pregnancy with Preeclampsia and a Subsequent Normal Pregnancy Women who have preeclampsia and who develop chronic hypertension later in life have an increased ventricular mass index before they become hypertensive .
Last, in at least some women with prior preeclampsia, hypertensive cardiovascular pathologies appear to have begun near the time of their own births.
A similar phenomenon is associated with preterm birth and with fetal-growth disorders.
Other cofactors or comorbidities are related to acquisition of these longterm adverse outcomes (Gastrich, 2012; Harskamp, 2007; Hermes, 2012; Spaan, 2012).
These include the metabolic syndrome, diabetes, obesity, dyslipidemia, and atherosclerosis (Catzov, 2021; Cho, 2019; Kajantie, 2017).
Women with pregnancy-associated hypertension are at increased risk for type 2 diabetes .
Preeclampsia predisposes for later diabetic retinopathy and retinal detachment (Auger, 2017; Beharier, 2016).
# Renal Sequelae.
Preeclampsia is a marker for subsequent renal disease.
Almost 15 percent of women with prior preeclampsia have renal dysfunction .
This may be related to AKI associated with preeclampsia (Novotny, 2020; Rodriquez, 2021).
In a Danish study with more than a million women, the chronic renal disease rate was sixfold greater in those who had preeclampsia .
These data need to be considered in light of the findings that 15 to 20 percent of women with preeclampsia who undergo renal biopsy have evidence of chronic renal disease .
In another long-term study, women with prior preeclampsia were significantly more likely to be chronically hypertensive—55 versus 7 percent —compared with control women.
They also had higher peripheral vascular and renovascular resistance and decreased renal blood flow.
These data do not permit conclusions as to cause versus effect .
# Central Nervous System Sequelae.
Eclamptic seizures were once believed to have no significant long-term CNS sequelae.
However, this likely is not the case (Bergman, 2021c; Theilen, 2016).
Recall that almost all eclamptic women have multifocal areas of perivascular edema, and approximately a fourth also have areas of cerebral infarction .
In several long-term studies in women with severe preeclampsia and eclampsia, white-matter lesions in the brain that followed eclamptic convulsions persist (Aukes, 2009, 2012).
Specifically, with magnetic resonance (MR) imaging, 40 percent of women with prior eclampsia had more numerous and larger aggregate white-matter lesions compared with 17 percent of normotensive control women.
These white-matter lesions were also found in women with preeclampsia without convulsions .
Others found temporal lobe white-matter changes and reduced cortical volume in women with prior preeclampsia .
In some, but not all studies, women with prior eclampsia had subjectively impaired cognitive functioning and increased risk for dementia (Basit, 2018; Elharram, 2018).
They also had a modest increase in the frequency of seizure disorders .
In another study, women with prior eclampsia had lower vision-related quality of life compared with control women .